Guide to the Saltar family correspondence, 1759-1880 and undated RL.10063
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Saltar family correspondence
1759-1880 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Saltar family
RL.10063
0.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Over 200 pieces of correspondence dating from 1759–1880, written by women of the Saltar and Gordon families of Pennsylvania, New Jersey, and Maryland between themselves and other family relations. Over a third of the letters date before 1825. The principal correspondents are Elizabeth 'Betsy" Gordon Saltar, her daughters Lucy Saltar and Frances "Fanny" Saltar, and Elizabeth's cousins Mary Gordon and Polly Gordon. Dozens of other letters come from family friends and relatives, male and female, from prominent families in Pennsylvania, New Jersey, Maryland, New York, and some from the Midwest and New England states. Topics include courtship; marriage; religion; pastimes; visits and travel; and the welfare of family members and friends. There are many references to illnesses, with many details on treatments and outcomes. There are also long passages and references to grief and mourning on the death of loved ones, and some discussions of finances. There are a few references to slavery and to enslaved people and servants. Letters sent during the Civil War discuss events centered around Pennsylvania, particularly in 1863; one discusses African American troops and their role in the war, and the circumstances surrounding the recruitment of the 3rd United States Colored Troops' commander, Benjamin C. Tilghman. A few earlier letters speak of the War of 1812, especially in and around Baltimore and Philadelphia. Acquired by the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Historical note
The Saltar (sometimes Salter) family of Pennsylvania and New Jersey traces its lineage back to Norfolk County, England. Their branch of the family in America begins with Richard Salter who settled in Monmouth County, New Jersey sometime between 1664 and 1687. The Saltars were economically and socially connected citizens and were closely involved, often through marriage, with many prominent families of the Philadelphia and New Jersey region: Drexels, Drinkers, Bownes, Bartons, Hartshornes, Logans, Morris, Tilghman, Usticks, Whartons, and others in Maryland, and Virginia. As Margaret Saltar married into the Lardner family in 1789 and had many children, there are correspondents from that family in the collection. The Gordon family was of Scottish descent, and its members were early settlers near what is now Princeton and Perth Amboy, New Jersey. The two families seem to have become firmly connected when Elizabeth Gordon married John Saltar in 1774. Their children were Maria (married Kearney Wharton), Lucy (died unmarried), John (married Margaret Howell), Lawrence (died at 22, unmarried), George (died at 22 unmarried), Frances (born c. 1790, died unmarried, 1880), and Gordon (died in childhood).
The Saltar family resided in the city of Philadelphia but also owned farms in the area, using enslaved people to work the land and serve in their houses. The plantation where they lived was known as "Magnolia Grove," near Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, already part of the family lands during the Revolutionary War. Other members of the family also lived in Pemberton and Tacony, New Jersey. In her rich reminiscences of colonial life published in the Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography (1916), Frances Saltar speaks of an African slave, African American slaves, and mulatto as well as English servants who were affiliated with her family. She also indicates that there were family members living in the West Indies.
Arrangement
Correspondence arranged by principal author, roughly by chronological period. The collection is rounded out by letters to unknown Saltar family women and other individuals, and four other non-correspondence manuscripts.
Collection Overview
The papers consist almost entirely of 266 pieces of correspondence dating from 1759–1880, written by women of the Saltar and Gordon families of Pennsylvania and Maryland between themselves and other family relations. Over one-third of the letters date before 1825. The principal correspondents are Elizabeth 'Betsy" Gordon Saltar, the family matriarch, Lucy Saltar, Frances "Fanny" Saltar, Mary Gordon, and Polly Gordon. There are also single letters from other female members of the Saltar family and a handful of letters from men, some of whom were Saltar family members. The letters are organized by correspondent name, ending with a group of letters addressed to unidentified individuals.
The manuscript pages total approximately 765, primarily bifolios, almost all written in ink. There are also four additional manuscripts: an invitation; a sheet of paper with receipts; and a memorandum and bond concerning a land sale. A number of later letters are accompanied by addressed envelopes, some with stamps.
The correspondence is almost entirely comprised of women writing to other women: mothers to daughters; daughters to mothers; and cousins to cousins; and friends to each other. Over half of the collection comprises letters to and from a family matriarch, Elizabeth Gordon Saltar, living at her residence at Magnolia Grove (near Frankford, Pa.), and a large group of letters sent by various correspondents to her daughter Fanny Saltar, who was one of the family's historians. Also present is a large group of correspondence between cousins Elizabeth Gordon Saltar and Mary Gordon, as well as letters addressed to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar's other daughter Lucy Saltar, and letters addressed to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar's cousins, Mary Gordon and Polly Gordon.
Other families who correspond and/or are mentioned often in the letters: Bowne, Brooks, Bunyan, Coleman, Drexel, Hartshorne, Howell, Lardner, McMurtrie, Morgan, Morris, Stillman, Tilghman, Ulstick, Van Dykes, and Wharton. Many of these are prominent families from Pennsylvania or Maryland. One letter from a Bowne in series 7 contains a partial family tree of the Bownes and Saltar families. Most of these letters are found in the Fanny Saltar series.
Among the places from which letters were sent are areas in Pennsylvania, Maryland, New York State, New Jersey, Illinois, Ohio, Connecticut, Massachusetts, Paris (France), and Rome (Italy). Cities represented are Boston, Baltimore, Charleston, New York, Brooklyn, Philadelphia, and others. Many letters were sent to or from Magnolia Grove, the Saltar plantation home near Philadelphia.
Topics tend to focus on societal mores and customs of the times as experienced by married and single women of land-owning classes: courtship; marriage; religion; pastimes; visits and travel; and the welfare of family members and friends. There are many references to illnesses such as measles, bowel complaints, eye conditions, diphtheria, tumors, and mental illness, with many details on treatments and outcomes. There are also long passages and references to grief and mourning on the death of loved ones, and fairly frequent mentions of finances.
The letters written during the Civil War discuss events centered around Pennsylvania, particularly in 1863, as well as a comment on friends going off to war, and one letter discusses African American troops and the circumstances surrounding the recruitment of the 3rd United States Colored Troops' commander, Benjamin C. Tilghman, whom the Saltars knew from Philadelphia. Earlier letters speak of the War of 1812, especially of events around Baltimore.
Acquired by the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Saltar family correspondence was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in May 2013.
Related Materials
Henry Benbridge Papers, Winterthur Library (almost half the letters are to his step-sister Elizabeth Gordon Saltar)
Maryland -- History -- War of 1812.; Pennsylvania -- History -- 1775-1865.; Pennsylvania -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Maryland -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.; Philadelphia (Pa.) -- History; Pennsylvania -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Participation, African American.; Slavery -- Pennsylvania.; Pennsylvania -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; New Jersey -- History -- 1775-1865.; Women -- United States -- Correspondence.; Families -- Pennsylvania -- Correspondence.; Maryland -- History -- 1775-1865; Medical care -- United States -- History -- 19th century.; Medical care -- United States -- History -- 18th century.; Women and death.; Slavery -- Maryland; Mothers and daughters; Gordon, Polly; Gordon, Mary; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Gordon family; Saltar, Elizabeth Gordon; Saltar, Lucy; Saltar, Frances
- Letters to Polly Gordon, 1759 May 5 - 1818 June 20, and undated; 12 items
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence group contains twelve letters to Polly Gordon, cousin of Saltar Family matriarch, Elizabeth Gordon Saltar. The first three letters of the series, all from Mary Penry, contain important notes on Christianity and women's roles and behaviors. The rest consists mostly of letters from Mrs. H. Stillman, Polly's aunt, and includes comments on illnesses, health and medicine, George Saltar's death, and Polly's engagement or marriage.
  - 1759 May 5: Mary Penry to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
    Presentation of the Gospel and Penry's own testimony. Penry describes herself as lowly and insignificant in comparison with her mighty Savior (Christ), and accordingly she can focus only on his grandeur. She hints that Polly may not have yet experienced the "true Happiness" of Christ, and that Polly is thus more concerned with the "World" than she need be.
  - 1762 March 1: Mary Penry (Bethlehem, PA) to Polly Gordon (Philadelphia) (Box 1)
    Inquiry about Polly's health after a bout with a "dangerous" illness. Penry implies that Polly is now a Christian (assuming she wasn't at the writing of the first letter). The letter includes a psalm-like poem and more discussion of Christianity.
  - 1765 August 25: Mary Penry (Litiz, PA) to Polly Gordon (Philadelphia) (Box 1)
  - 1766 March 11: Mrs. H. Stillman (Boston) to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
    Passing mention that a sick daughter has been confined to her bedroom for three months.
  - 1807 July 26: George Morgan Gibbs (Charleston, S.C.) to Polly Gordon ("near Princeton") (Box 1)
    George Morgan Gibbes, a cousin, writes for his mother, Mrs. Gibbes, who continues to love her daughter with "unalterable affection." Discusses briefly the children of the family, their governess/teacher, lessons in piano and dance, and studies at the "college" in Charleston.
  - 1818 June 20: W.M. Beatty [?] to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
    A business letter in which he is returning papers that were in his possession having to do with the sale of land, possibly related to the bond in the letters to Mary Gordon which bears Beatty's name.
  - Undated: H. Stillman to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: H. Stillman to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
    Seems to be discussing Polly's engagement or marriage.
  - Undated: H. Stillman to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: H. Stillman to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: H. Stillman to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: Frances Saltar (Magnolia Grove) to Polly Gordon (Box 1)
    Entire letter gives details of George Saltar's medical care and death: Doctor Glen (Philadelphia?) advised that George be bled and "kept still," but he was allowed to come home. Once home, other doctors provided blistering and cupping treatments. He was sick for twenty-one days, and then died.
- Letters to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar, 1770 June - 1810 February 8; 5 items
  Five letters to Elizabeth ("Betsy") Gordon Saltar, the matriarch of the Saltar family, then living at Magnolia Grove plantation, which was about seven miles from Philadelphia, PA and in the vicinity of Frankford. The majority of contents are routine updates about family and friends. The first letter, however, is addressed to Betsy Gordon, who was as yet unmarried, and thus contains notes on reasons for marriage and the aspirations of a single woman. The third, received from Frances Edwards, contains descriptions of grief on the recent death in the Lardner family and memories of her own loss of a husband, and the similar loss experienced by Elizabeth Saltar.
  - 1770 June: Peggy Emlen (Philadelphia) to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (Box 1)
    Evidence of Emlen's idealism: the beauty of the world is a reflection of God; wishes to spend time in the country to reflect on nature; a man and a women should marry for love of each other's virtues; pray that passions are overcome by reason.
  - 1800 May 10: Lucy Saltar (Baltimore) to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1803 April 27: Frances [?] Edwards to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (Box 1)
    A discussion of Edwards' grief and mourning over the death of her husband last Spring: "he was my all," "I... lay in my bed and think of him." She seems to writing on the occasion of a more recent death in the Saltar family and mentions Hannah Lardner as well as the Saltars.
  - 1806 August 9: Mary Gordon (Mapletown, NJ) to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1810 February 8: Mary Gordon to Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (Box 1)
- Letters from Elizabeth Gordon Saltar, 1806 February - 1818 September 5, and undated; 66 items
  These letters written by Elizabeth Gordon Saltar consist almost entirely of correspondence sent to her cousin Mary Gordon. The letters chiefly contain updates about friends and family. Four mentions are made of the War of 1812, specifically relating to the attack on Baltimore. Many more are made of health issues, including mentions of small pox, bleeding by leeches, and other remedies of the time. Also prevalent are comments on Christianity, marriage and courtship, and other aspects of 17th century women's society such as pastimes and duties at home. Unless otherwise noted, letters from Elizabeth Gordon Saltar are sent from Magnolia Grove, the family's plantation near Philadelphia. Letters to Mary Gordon, unless otherwise noted, are sent to Mapletown, a small community near Princeton, New Jersey.
  - 1806 February: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Lucy Saltar (New York) (Box 1)
  - 1806 March 5: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Lucy Saltar (New York) (Box 1)
  - 1806 June 4: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Saltar's son Lawrence died at 22 of yellow fever; the next son, John, spent a year in Calcutta.
  - 1806 September: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Cure for ague: "30 grains of salt of wormwood, 20 ditto of Virginia snake root, ½ an ounce of red bark; mix them with three glasses of Madeira wine; take a glass every four hours, the day the fit is off, shake it well every time you take it"
  - 1806 October 19: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Discussion of intimacy with "beaus."
  - 1806 October 26: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Frances Saltar (Phildelphia) (Box 1)
    Fanny went into the city to paint.
  - 1807 January 4: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1807 May 10: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1807 August 2: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1807 December 3: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1808 May 22: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Mr. Saltar's sickness and its remedies.
  - 1808 September 4: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Mr. Saltar still having trouble "passing his water"; mentioning tenant farmers (African-Americans)—still says "our" when referring to them ("we had the misfortune to lose our little black boy").
  - 1808 September 25: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Mr. Saltar is being treated with "medicine, bleeding [took 35 oz. in one day and used leeches], and dieting"
  - 1809 January 8: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon
    Discussing the embargo in Philadelphia and its pervasive effects
  - 1809 August 16: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1809 September 19: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Includes a recipe for blue dye that is a "Cure for Wen" (a cyst, especially on the face).
  - 1809 November 8: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1809 November 9: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Looking for a maid: "white or black." Also, further mentions of African-American relations to whites.
  - 1809 November 25: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1809 December 7: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Saltar's daughter Lucy has made no "conquests," i.e. securing a "beau."
  - 1810 January 4: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1810 February 13: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Little girl dies from "violent sick stomach."
  - 1810 March 22: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1810 December 10: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Looking for a black horseman and maid.
  - 1811 January 22: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1811 March 2: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1811 April 22: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1811 May 28: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Woman dies in child birth.
  - 1811 June 17: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Saltar has an "indolent tumor," so she is dieting and taking medicine.
  - 1812: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
  - 1812 November 7: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1812 December 26: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1813 March 24: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Frances Saltar (Box 1)
    Passing mention to the British during the War of 1812.
  - 1813 April 5: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1813 June 12: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1813 July 20: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1813 September 2: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1813 November 27: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1814 January 10: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Passing mentions of the War of 1812
  - 1814 April 5: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1814 April 16: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1814 July 7: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1814 September: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    War of 1812 British invasion of Baltimore repulsed by Americans; mothers worry over sons being called to fight.
  - 1814 November 19: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1814 December 24: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1815 February 28: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Celebrating victory in the War of 1812, but lamenting the merchant community and its great suffering.
  - 1815 August 14: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1815 August 28: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1815 December 22: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 February 7: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 April 9: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 May 1: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 June 13: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 July 4: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1816 November 2: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1817 January 17: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1817 April 10: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Great deal of small pox near Magnolia Grove. All ages are contracting the disease, but only some choose to be vaccinated or innoculated. Instead, they diet and prepare themselves "in the natural way."
  - 1817 May 3: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Further description of small pox near Magnolia Grove, including more mentions of vaccination, innoculation, and death. Also, Saltar mentions an infected boy that was "deaf and dumb" from birth, and that it would be a "blessing" for God to take him.
  - 1817 June 1: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1817 October 21: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1817 December 31: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1818 June 8: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1818 September 5: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - Undated: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Mrs. VanDyke (Box 1)
  - Undated: Elizabeth Gordon Saltar to Polly Gordon
    Custodial History
    Copy of original letter, which is entirely religious in nature. Contains a transcription of a sermon by Doc. Blair called "The Compassion of Christ."
- Letters to Lucy Saltar, 1806 November 4 - 1822 June 18 and undated; 4 items
  Series contains four letters to Lucy Saltar, daughter of Elizabeth Gordon Saltar. The first letters contain some comments about courting behaviors. Most other content consists of routine updates about family and friends.
  - 1806 November 4: Jane Hartshorne to Lucy Saltar (New York to Magnolia Grove, PA) (Box 1)
    Discussion of Lucy's "admired" - the young man courting her.
  - 1811 March 4: Jane Hartshorne to Lucy Saltar (New York to Magnolia Grove, PA) (Box 1)
    Coping with the death of loved ones.
  - 1822 June 18: Mrs. F. [?] Ustick to Lucy Saltar (Shrewsbury, MA to Holmesburg, PA) (Box 1)
    "My dear cousin." Long commentary on her failure to provide a "suitable situation" for a destitute niece and other children in her niece's family due to her limited means, and thanking her cousins for taking up her cause.
  - Undated: Fanny Saltar to Lucy Saltar (Magnolia Grove to Wilmington, DE) (Box 1)
    Young women discussing courtship.
  - Undated: Mrs. J. Bunyan (Morganza Mills, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Bears the news of the death of John Morgan, son-in-law of Mrs. Bunyan, after a two-year invalid illness, and a narrative of a forced land sale by George Gibbes of Charleston that "broke his heart."
- Letters to Mary Gordon, 1808 March 14 - 1819 August 21; 13 items
  Group of 10 letters addressed to Mary Gordon, cousin of Elizabeth Gordon Saltar. Contains substantial material concerning finance and economics, including a bond from 1818 that involved a land sale to John Morgan, more of which is found in letters to Fanny Saltar. Also of note is a description of the after-effects of Elizabeth Saltar's eye surgery. Unless otherwise noted, all letters to Mary Gordon are sent to Mapletown near Princeton, NJ. (Note: All letters to Mary Gordon from Elizabeth Gordon Saltar are in Series 3.)
  - 1808 March 14: Eliza Newman (Cambridge, MA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1810 May 20: Maria Morgan (Morganza, near Cannonsburg, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1810 September 4: Maria Morgan (Morganza, near Cannonsburg, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - 1811 July 28: John Saltar (Magnolia Grove, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Describes the eye surgery of and its after-effects on Elizabeth Gordon Saltar (his mother).
  - 1814 December 8: George Morgan (Morganza, near Cannonsburg, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Land sale, laws, and the possibility of fraud.
  - 1819 August 21: Fanny Saltar (Tacony, Philadelphia, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - Probably June, no year: John Morgan (Canonsburg, PA) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
    Writes chiefly about family, describing health and what various children are studying and doing. Mentions financial payments to Mary and a bond.
  - September, no year: Fanny Saltar (Magnolia Grove) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)
  - December 1, no year: Ann Gibbes (Charleston, SC) to Mary Gordon (Box 1)